## M. Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

NSF MPS Ascend Postdoctoral Fellow · University of California, Riverside

■ mwimb002@ucr.edu | ★ mkrodriguezwimberly.github.io | ★ @astronomouse | ORCID: 0000-0003-1848-5571

### Research Statement(s)\_

I study Near-Field Cosmology and Galaxy Evolution using both optical telescopes and cosmological simulations. In particular, my work focuses on ultra-faint dwarf galaxies — researching these possible relics of the first galaxies ever formed to learn more about the Early Universe, how the earliest galaxies evolve, and how they can be used as a tool to learn more about our own galaxy, the Milky Way.

Alongside this astrophysics research, I work to improve the astronomical community for all, including publishing articles to help spread successful programs. I have created peer mentorship programs implemented at my alma mater, UC Irvine, wand within the Cal-Bridge Program. My aim is to normalize a holistic approach to academic success and strengthen marginalized communities.

#### Education

#### **University of California, Irvine**

Irvine, California

Ph.D. in Physics

Sep 2016 - Dec 2021

- · Thesis Advisor: Prof. Michael Cooper
- Thesis: Ultra-Faint Dwarf Galaxies: Investigating the Evolution of Our Universe & Those Who Study It

#### University of California, Irvine

Irvine, California

M.S. in Physics

Sep 2016 - June 2019

Aug 2015 - May 2016

• GPA: 3.34 out of possible 4.00

#### **California State University, Long Beach**

Long Beach, California

M.S. in Physics

- GPA: 4.00 out of possible 4.00
- Transferred to Ph.D. Program

#### California State University, Long Beach

Long Beach, California

**B.S.** in Physics

- · Minor: Math
- Overall GPA: 3.15 out of possible 4.00
- Major GPA: 3.20 out of possible 4.00

**Mount San Antonio College** 

#### Walnut, California

Jan 2011 - May 2015

ΑА

Jan 2004 - June 2009

- Majors: Fine Arts, Natural Science & Math, Social & Behavioral Sciences
- Overall GPA: 3.32 out of possible 4.00

#### **Publications**

#### A Model of Mentorship for Students from Historically Underrepresented Groups in STEM Rodriguez Wimberly, M.K., et al.

Understanding Interventions

- · Under Review
- arXiv: 2209.03395

#### Sizing from the Smallest Scales: The Mass of the Milky Way

MNRAS, 513, 4968

Rodriguez Wimberly, M.K., et al.

#### Characterizing the Infall Times and Quenching Timescales of the Milky Way Satellites with Gaia Proper Motions

Suppressing Star Formation on the Smallest Scales: What Role Does Environment Play?

**MNRAS** 

Fillingham, S.P. et al.

2019

- · Under Review
- arXiv: 1906..04180

# SETI Observations of Exoplanets with the Allen Telescope Array

MNRAS, 483, 4031 2019

Rodriguez Wimberly, M.K., et al.

AJ, 152.6 (2016b): 181

Harp, G.R. et al.

2016

RODRIGUEZ WIMBERLY CV OCTOBER 15, 2022 1/7

### **Highlighted Awards**

NSF MPS Ascend Postdoctoral Fellow, 2021 - Current AAS National Osterbrock Fellow, 2020 - 2021 NSF Graduate Research Fellow, 2016 - 2021 Eugene Cota-Robles Fellow, 2016 - 2021

### **Teaching Experience**

#### **ASTR110L: Introduction to Astronomy Lab**

CSU Long Beach

Instructor on Record

Aug 2015 - May 2016

- Duties included creating and implementing syllabi based off the department's experiment schedule, homework assignments, exams and final projects (sample syllabi can be viewed at https://mkrodriguezwimberly.github.io/outreach\_teaching\_service/astro100Lsyllabus.html).
- CSULB Official Instructor Evaluations were given after each term and I was guided on how to interpret the feedback and implement desired improvements by the CSULB Physics & Astronomy Department Chair.

### Highlighted Mentorship \_\_\_\_\_

#### **Cal-Bridge Mentorship Handbook**

Revision Team Lead June 2021

- · Led team of 4 other Cal-Bridge Alumni in rewriting the program's mentorship handbook with the guidance of the program's director.
- Revisions focus on reciprocal mentor-mentee relationships (especially in that as much as students need to adapt to academia, mentors and academia need to adapt to students), highlighting hurdles specific to many underrepresented groups within STEM, and mental health
- Publicly available at https://tinyurl.com/CBMentorshipHandbook

#### **Cal-Bridge Mentor Map**

Author Aug 2020

- Created a Mentor/Support Network Map designed specifically for undergraduate STEM students.
- Publicly available at https://tinyurl.com/CBMentorshipMap

### Observing Experience \_\_\_\_

1.5 Nights **Keck Observatory**, Chemical Abundances in UFD, Willman 1
15 Nights **Keck Observatory**, Extragalactic Star Formation Quenching Survey
Oct 2015 **UCO/Lick Observatory**, Robert P. Kraft Observational Astronomy Workshop

DEIMOS, Lead Co-I

DEIMOS, Co-I

#### Skills

**Programming** 

Python (Pandas, SciPy, NumPy, Scikit-learn, AstroPy), IRAF (DEIMOS Mask Design, Wavelength Calibration), MySQL, Fortran95, Mathematica, HTML, Certified LabVIEW Associate Developer

Tools

Unix, Shell (Bash/Zsh), LTEX(Overleaf/R Markdown), Pypelt, Aladin, DS9, Gwyddion, Git, Atomic & Magnetic Force Microscopy.

Soft Skills

Time Management, Teamwork, Problem-solving, Documentation, Engaging Presentation.

### **Society Memberships**

| <b>Astronomical Society of the Pacific</b> , Board of Directors Member, Diversity Committee Co-Chair | 2017 - Present |
|--|----------------|
| American Astronomical Society, Member  | 2015 - Present |
| American Physical Society, Member  | 2015 - 2017    |
| Society of Physics Students - CSULB, CSULB Chapter Secretary (2013-2015), Member                     | 2011 - 2015    |

#### Invited Talks\_

| Astronomy Colloquium, University of Michigan, Department of Astronomy   | September 2022 |
|---|----------------|
| Conversations in Equity & Inclusion, University of Michigan, Department of Astronomy  | September 2022 |
| Astronomy Brown Bag Lunch, MIT  | May 2022       |
| Physics & Astronomy Colloquium, Pomona College  | April 2022     |
| Cosmology & Astronomy Seminar, University of California, Davis  | October 2021   |
| Cosmology & Astronomy Seminar, University of California, Davis  | October 2021   |
| CCAPP Little Galaxies Meeting, The Ohio State University  | October 2021   |
| <b>Lunchtime Seminar</b> , The Carnegie Observatories   | September 2021 |
| <b>Lunchtime Seminar</b> , The Carnegie Observatories   | February 2020  |
| <b>Barriers to Equity, Inclusion &amp; Diversity in Astronomy,</b> Plenary Speaker, Presented on Imposter Syndrome, Astronomical Society of the Pacific $130^{th}$ Annual Meeting | September 2018 |

#### **Recent Contributed Presentations**

| <b>Keck Science Meeting</b> , Oral Presentation   | September 2022 |  |
|---|----------------|--|
| GalFESCA Conference, Oral Presentation  | September 2022 |  |
| ${f 240}^{th}$ Meeting of the American Astronomical Society, Dissertation Contributed Oral Presentation | June 2022      |  |
| Science by Diverse Scientists: A Cal-Bridge Physics & Astronomy Seminar, Oral Presentation              | April 2022     |  |
| Galaxy Formation & Evolution in the Era of the Roman Space Telescope, Oral Presentation                 | October 2020   |  |
| Space Telescope Science Institute's 2020 Spring Symposium — The Local Group: Assembly &                 | September 2020 |  |
| <b>Evolution</b> , Poster Presentation  | September 2020 |  |

### **Highlighted Service Activities**\_

#### **Cal-Bridge Mentorship Committee Co-Chair**

2020 - Present

Cal-Bridge Program: A bridge program assisting undergraduate STEM students into graduate programs

- Led revision of program's mentorship handbook
- Led creation and execution of professional development workshop focused on relational mentoring using the revised mentorship handbook

#### **Astronomical Society of the Pacific Board of Directors Member**

2019 - Present

Diversity Committee Co-Chair

#### **Cal-Bridge Director of Peer Mentoring Program**

2019 - Present

Creator & Organizer of Peer Mentoring Program for Cal-Bridge Scholars

#### **APS-IDEA Network: UCI Team Member**

2020-2021

Network creating equitable, inclusive and diverse communities

#### **UCI Physics & Astronomy Community Excellence**

2018-2021

- Co-Creator of Peer Mentoring Programs for 1st Year Physics Graduate Students
- Group Sessions & 1-on-1 Mentoring with Trained Peer Mentors
- Our Website: uci-pace.github.io

### **Highlighted Media Pieces**

#### **Mercury Magazine Contributor (Research Focus)**

Astronomical Society of the Pacific

2018 - Present

Author: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

#### **Road to Happiness: Featured Alumni Story**

California Sate University STEM Network

August 2022 Author: Monica Alarcon

#### The Reionization of Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

UC Irvine School of Physical Sciences Features

September 2021

Author: Lucas Van Wyk Joel

#### **Ultra-Faint Dwarf Galaxies: Cosmic Fossils?**

AstronoMouse YouTube SciComm Playlist

2018-2020 Creator: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

#### **Katy Rodriguez Wimberly: Changing My Life for Science**

The Story Collider: True, Personal Stories About Science

May 2017

Speaker: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

### **Employment History**

| UCI Competitive Edge Program, Graduate Student Peer Mentor                      | 2017 & 2018 |
|---|-------------|
| UCI Competitive Edge Program, Graduate Student Researcher                       | 2016        |
| CSLUB Physics Dept., Teaching Assistant - Astronomy Lab Instructor              | 2015-2016   |
| UCI Summer Internship Program, Cal-Bridge Student Researcher                    | 2015        |
| US Army Reserves, Staff Sergeant, Saxophonist, Human Resources Manager          | 2003-2015   |
| CSLUB Physics Dept., Learning Assistant   | 2013-2015   |
| SETI Institute REU, CAMPARE Student Researcher                                  | 2014        |
| LSAMP Academic Year Fellowship, Student Researcher                              | 2013-2014   |
| University of Texas, Brownsville Physics REU, Student Researcher                | 2012        |
| <b>CSULB Physics Dept.</b> , Winter Research Student Researcher                 | 2012        |
| Dept. of Defense Army Civilian, 300th Army Band Unit Administrator              | 2009-2012   |
| Anbeten Productions, Design Assistant/Consultant                                | 2006-2009   |
| Disneyland Attractions Dept., Innoventions Supervisor, Project Lead & Performer | 2007-2009   |
| Mt. San Antonio College Theatre Dept., Asst. Costumer                           | 2006        |
| Disneyland Entertainment Dept., Costumer & Atmosphere Character                 | 2003-2006   |

#### References\_

**Dr. Laura Sales**Professor - UC Riverside

lsales@ucr.edu - 951.827.7037

**Dr. Michael Cooper**Professor - UC Irvine

cooper@uci.edu - 949.824.6485

**Dr. Alex Ji**Professor - University of Chicago

alexji@uchicago.edu - 773.702.8203

**Dr. Alex Rudolph**Professor - Cal Poly Pomona

alrudolph@cpp.edu - 909.717.1851

#### **Previous Awards**

UCI Latino Excellence & Achievement Award, 2020

**UCI Physics & Astronomy Department Award for Outstanding Contributions**, 2019

UCI Graduate Division Tom Angell Mentor Fellowship, 2019

**Doctoral Diversity Initiative Fellow**, 2016

**Diversity Recruitment Fellowship**, 2016

**Nevin Graduate Endowment Fellowship**, 2016

CSU-UC Cal-Bridge Scholar, 2014 - 2017

LSAMP PROUD Scholar Award, 2015

CSULB Physical Sciences and Mathematics Scholar , 2014

**CSULB Physics Department Scholarship**, 2014

Louis Stokes' Alliance for Minority Participation Academic Year Fellow, 2013 - 2014

**CSULB Physics Department Scholarship**, 2013

#### **Past Service Activities**

**DreamWakers Speaker** 2017 - Present

Virtual chats with grade school science classrooms.

## EmpowHER: Empowering Women through High School Engagement and STEM Research-Keynote Speaker

University of California, Irvine

Inaugural Annual Conference to enhance student success in STEM

2020

**UCI Competitive Edge Workshop Leader**Created and Lead Workshop on Impostor Phenomena

APS Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics at UCI

2020

2022

Local Organizing Committee

**UCI Astronomy Outreach** 

• Assisted in proposal, promotion, recruitment, and programming

Co-Leader of ASCEND@UCI Mini Conference - Our Website: https://sites.uci.edu/cuwip2020/ascend-at-uci/

#### Astronomical Society of the Pacific Junior Board Fellow

2017-2019

First ever Junior Board Fellow on the ASP Board of Directors

#### **Bruin Brains Research Conference - Keynote Speaker**

2019

TRIO Programming at Salt Lake Community College, UT

#### **Expand Your Horizons Event - Keynote Speaker**

2019
Salt Lake Community College, UT

Annual Workshop for 6-10th Grade Girls Interested in STEM

2017-2019

A Graduate Student Representative

#### **UCI Physics & Astronomy Inclusive Excellence Committee**

,

Department Committee to Improve Climate and Diversity

Mentorship Chair

2017-2019

## **UCI Physics & Astronomy Physics Graduate Caucus**Department Organization to Improve Graduates' Experience

2018-2019

Department organization to improve oraduates. Experience

A Graduate Student Representative

**UCI Physics & Astronomy Admission Task Force**Department Committee to Improve Diversity in Admissions

Telescope Volunteer for Elementary-level Classroom Night Sky Viewing Parties

#### **Astronomy Outreach for Underrepresented Youth**

2016-2019

2016-2019

K-12 Classroom Visits for underrepresented groups ranging from ethnic minorities to Autistic and Downs Syndrome students.

#### Letters to a Pre-Scientist Scientist Pen Pal

2015-2019

Pen Pal during each Academic Year with a grade school student interested in space science.

| UCI DECADE Learning Community - Invited Workshop Leader Created and Lead Workshop on Facing Impostor Phenomena      | 2018      |
|---|-----------|
| Reclaiming STEM Science Communication Workshop - Invited Speaker Presented "Building Your Social Media Brand"       | 2018      |
| UCI Physics & Astronomy Stride! Peer Mentoring Mentoring & Activities Focused on Graduate Applications & Transition | 2018      |
| UCSC Osterbrock Sierra Conference Planning Comittee, Co-I Lead Professional Development Planning & Execution        | 2017      |
| SPS CSULB Chapter Secretary  • Assist in outreach program & event planning & execution                              | 2013-2015 |

Assist in chapter and physics department event planning and execution

2013 - 2014

Workshop Leader for Mexican American Engineers & Scientists CSULB Chapter

#### Past Contributed Presentations \_\_\_\_

**CSULB Science Outreach** 

| <b>Keck Science Meeting,</b> Oral Presentation  | September 2022 |
|---|----------------|
| Cal-Bridge's Science by Diverse Scientists, Oral Presentation   | September 2020 |
| GalFRESCA @ UCI, Oral Presentation  | August 2019    |
| <b>Keck Science Meeting</b> , Poster Presentation   | September 2018 |
| <b>UCSC Galaxy Workshop</b> , Oral Presentation, Recording of the presentation can be found here!                   | August 2018    |
| GalFRESCA, CalTech, Oral Presentation   | August 2017    |
| UCI Summer Research Symposium, Poster Presentation  | August 2016    |
| <b>227</b> <sup>th</sup> <b>AAS Meeting</b> , Poster Presentation   | January 2016   |
| APS Far West Meeting, Oral Presentation   | October 2015   |
| CAMPARE Research Symposium, Oral Presentation   | September 2015 |
| UCI Summer Research Symposium, Oral Presentation  | September 2015 |
| CSULB Student Research Symposium, Poster Presentation   | October 2014   |
| Astrobiology Science Conference, Oral Presentation  | June 2015      |
| CAMPARE Research Symposium, Oral Presentation   | September 2014 |
| <b>SETI Institute REU Symposium</b> , Oral Presentation, <i>Lightening Talk</i> version found here at 22:00 minutes | August 2014    |
| CSULB Student Research Symposium, Poster Presentation   | October 2013   |
| Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics , Poster Presentation   | January 2013   |
| University of Texas, Brownsville REU Symposium, Oral Presentation   | January 2013   |

### Past Media Pieces\_

Astronomy on Tap! March 2021

AoT Davis AoT West LA Co-Presenter: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

| Katy Rodriguez Wimberly Receives Latino Excellence and Achievement Award | May 2020 |
|--|----------|
|--|----------|

UC Irvine School of Physical Sciences News

Author: Lucas Van Wyk Joel

PACE Yourself April 2020

UC Irvine School of Physical Sciences Features

Author: Lucas Van Wyk Joel

M. Katy Rodriguez Wimberly Profile

May 2020

1 Million Women in STEM

Author: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

The Cal-Bridge Program Summer 2020

Cultivating Excelencia Podcast Interview

Producer: Michelle Espino Lira

Astronomouse Winter 2019

American Physical Society Forum on Graduate Student Affairs Newsletter

Author: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

**Interview with Katy Rodriguez Wimberly** 

Exploring New Worlds: An Astrophysicist's Journey from Academia to Industry

Interviewer: Ines Juvan-Beaulieu

Reclaiming STEM: addressing the gap in diverse and inclusive trainings

June 2019

September 2019

Authors: Evelyn Valdez-Ward AND Linh

Anh Cat

**Student Spotlight: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly** 

April 2019

UCI Physics & Astronomy Blog

California Program Cultivates Minority Physics and Astronomy Ph.D. Students

October 2018

Diverse Issues in Higher Education

Cal-Bridge: Changing the Face of STEM One Student At A Time

May 2018

STEM For All Multiplex

Sister STFM

Peer Pressure Ep 38: Astronomy, Not Astrology with Katy Wimberly

February 2018

Peer Pressure Podcast

Brandon Ongsy

Interviewers: Dominic Lozano and

**Great Gram!** 

**OC** Register

Careers with STEM

November 2017

Interviewer: Eliza Brockwell

Hundreds gather at UCI to witness 'Great American Eclipse'

August 2017
Author: Tomoya Shimura

Student Highlight: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

April 2016

Astronomy in Color

Interviewer: Jorge Moreno

**CSU LSAMP PROUD - Program Recognizing Outstanding Undergraduate Distinction** 

October 2015

California State University Louis Stokes Alliance For Minority Participation